[Music]
Stanford
University okay we have 10 minutes uh
for
uh
schmoozing you a com
last
okay in in a in a scenario where you
just got
a in a horizon
call
Universe how is it
hot do you mean how hot is it or how is
it hot how is it hot like what's the
mechanism of it being
hot exactly the same as in the black
hole does that help
you all right
let's black I kind of the energy of
gravity
all
right you
know that's pretty much exactly what I
was going to start uh the lecture with
tonight so make sure I start on that but
I'm going to defer it until uh until 7
because that was about where I was going
to begin black
ho on the black hole temperature you
said you lower the temp uh thermometer
The
Horizon if you did that experiment you
shot photons at the black hole to build
it up yes and uh you would still measure
the same entropy entropy wait let let's
be precise there's entropy there's
energy there's temperature what are you
asking exactly first we measure the same
entity because it would still be the
same probability of the photon either
being captured or
missing after the photon falls into the
horizon or onto the horizon or whatever
you want to call it the entropy or
the hidden information if you like the
information that's inaccessible to you
because it's either inside the black
hole
or uh from your perspective very very
close to the Horizon and it would take
forever for a photon to get
out uh the information that's hidden is
one more bit so every time you drop a
single Photon in the entropy increases
by one unit so it's the energy that are
you is like you're seeing a higher
frequency Photon because you're near the
Horizon yes
yes yes the question about the the
temperature of
Horizons um well let me answer it
now the Horizon is always hot I'm we
going to come back to it in a minute The
Horizon is always hot in the sense that
if you lower the thermometer down you
would always always detect a very very
high temperature as you get very close
to the Horizon so you can think of it as
the Horizon being a
place or Surface of extremely high
temperature which is constantly emitting
and reabsorbing
photons um they're really Quantum
fluctuations and they're really nothing
more than the highfrequency quantum
fluctuations that are taking place in a
small volume of space in a small region
of
space uh The
Horizon makes them real in a way which
I'll come to which which we're going to
talk about makes them real thermal
fluctuations in a rather interesting way
but every
Horizon always has the property that the
temperature the actual temperature of a
real thermometer lowered down to the
Horizon would record a temperature which
would be 1
ided by 2 pi * the distance to the
Horizon the distance to the Horizon in
the
denominator every Horizon whether it's a
black hole horizon or any any other
kind uh always has that
property um you asked me a question now
I can't remember exactly what it was I
think when you're near the Horizon the
time uh sort of freezes does that mean
that the photon that came in build yeah
yeah let's forget the photon that came
in to build it up let's talk about the
photons which are being
emitted why when you stand far from The
Horizon does the Horizon not or does the
radiation that hits you why isn't it
this very high frequency
radiation that is emitted very close to
the Horizon other words you drop a temp
the thermometer down you discover that
the region near The Horizon the
so-called near Horizon region is very
very hot
why isn't it hot far away I can assure
you if we created a blank wall over
there or that wall and we heated it up
to some very very high temperature and
let's suppose it was a very very big
wall and we heated it up to some high
temperature I don't think it would make
much sense to say that as we moved away
from the Black from the wall that the
temperature went down like one over the
uh the distance it wouldn't you would be
blinded by high fre queny photons pretty
much no matter how far you got from that
wall The High Frequency photons that
came out of it the gamma rays the super
gamma rays everything else that came out
of it would blind you no matter pretty
much no matter how far you got from the
U from the from this very very large
wall um why is it that that doesn't
happen with a horizon of a black hole
why when you ST stand back from it and
get a good deal of distance between you
U and the
Horizon why don't you get blinded by
these very high frequency photons and
the answer what's the answer sh red
shift red shift the red shift is another
way of saying that as the photons
propagate away from the Horizon they
lose energy and they lose energy for
exactly the same reason kinetic
energy they lose energy for exactly the
same reason that this piece of chalk
does when you throw it up in the
air it is doing work or you have in
order to raise it you have to do work
against the gravitational field and if
you don't do work to keep it moving with
the same velocity then the velocity will
slow down well with photons don't don't
think about velocity velocity is a wrong
thing to think about think about energy
for a non relativistic piece of chalk
there's a close relationship between its
velocity and its energy but what's
really happening is it's losing energy
right for a photon the relation between
velocity and energy is
different namely the velocity is always
the speed of light and the energy is the
energy but it's still true that as the
photon climbs out of the
gravitational influence of the black
hole it loses energy so in the transit
between the Horizon very near the
Horizon where it's very hot and far away
the photon loses an amount of
energy such that a distant Observer
doesn't see the black hole as being very
hot he sees it having the Hawking
temperature and the Hawking temperature
decreases with the mass of the black
hole remember what it was the Hawking
temperature of a black hole and you can
think of it as the temperature as seen
by somebody looking at the photons or
being exposed to the photons very far
from the black hole the temperature T
Hawking is equal I'll write the precise
formula for no particular reason but uh
1 over 8
pi times the mass of the black hole
there is an H bar here a plunks
constant and some numbers of factors of
C which I can never remember C cubed I
can't remember it's or downstairs bar
just plain H because the pi is already
in I don't remember I think it's h bar I
think it's h bar I think it's actually H
bar
right uh 8 pi times the mass of the
black hole so the bigger the black hole
the cooler it is why does it look cooler
for a big black hole well that Photon
that was created very near the Horizon
has a more difficult time
getting away from the big black hole
than a smaller black hole in other words
it has to do has to do more work it
loses more energy in escaping from a big
black hole from the near Horizon region
than it does for a small black hole so
the effect is the temperature the
effective temperature seen by an
observer far
away decreases with the mass of the
black hole but if you take this formula
you interpret it in terms of the energy
of typical
photons in fact the temperature of black
body radiation the temperature of
thermal
radiation is approximately the same as
the typical energy of Any Given
Photon so this just says the photons
typically have
energy one over the mass of the black
hole and if you then Trace that inward
toward the Horizon and say how much
energy did the Photon have to
have when it started out in order to
escape and have this much energy when it
got out you'll find the energy is always
the same it's
always about this one over 2 pi times
the distance from The Horizon how close
can you get to the Horizon in a
meaningful sense well the plun distance
the plun distance sets the scale for all
quantum mechanical distances
and so you might say then that these
photons originated in a thin layer this
is the way it behaves this is the way
the system behaves they and a thin layer
perhaps a plunk length thick near the
horizon or right at the Horizon and it
is continuously emitting photons and
absorbing photons emitting and absorbing
them
uh the energy of the photons as high as
you can imagine the plunk energy now
most of those photons don't get
out most of those photons don't get out
what happens to
them they fall
back all right here's the
Horizon of a large black
hole and if the Horizon is hot it's
continuously emitting photons but though
some of those photons go radially out
but very very few of them most of them
go off at some
angle the ones that go off at an angle
are pretty much guaranteed to fall back
into the Horizon of the black hole it's
only a tiny cone of angles
here that uh that photons will
escape so in fact the emission of
photons is a very slow process it's a
slow process because most of them don't
come out at an angle which is
appropriate for them to escape
and most of them simply just fall back
to the Horizon fall back because of
gravitation the ones that are coming
out can bang into the ones falling in
and guess what
happens they Collide they're very
energetic they make electron positron
pairs they make everything that you can
think about and they make this thin
layer of very very hot
material it's like no material that we
ordinarily encounter in nature
much much hotter and the surface of it
is continuously emitting photons which
we see as having much much lower energy
than their
emission that's the mathematical Theory
that's the consequence of the
mathematical theory of Horizons there's
another way to think about it
remember we've drawn pictures of black
holes
uh the outside of the black hole was out
here the inside of the black hole was in
here somebody a given distance from the
black hole is moving along a trajectory
which looks like
this now there are quantum fluctuations
that take place without trying to get
into the depths of quantum field Theory
let's just use um the rough metaphor of
quantum fluctuations being closed Loops
of virtual particles so virtual
particles are constantly being created
and
annihilated and obser a far away just
sees those particles create doesn't see
them actually it all happens too fast
right
here's here are the lines of constant
time way out here is T equals
infinity all right somebody out here
here a little fluctuation like that
lasts a tiny amount of time you they can
be detected they can be detected by you
know very high Precision Quantum
electrodynamics and the properties of
atoms and so forth but there are also
fluctuations that take place over
here
now those fluctuations appear to be
emitted from The Horizon The Horizon is
a place very close to this light cone
here they appear to be emitted and fall
back into the
Horizon that is exactly what these
things are they are the quantum
fluctuations which take place half
behind the Horizon and half in front of
the Horizon and look to somebody on the
outside as something emitted from The
Horizon and
reabsorbed some tiny fraction of them
have enough energy to get out and we
call P that Hawking radiation if you're
on the outside would you see it go from
T minus infinity to t plus infinity
sorry again when it crosses those uh
those 45° lines said there tals the
lower one yeah well okay so let's not
yeah there's a classical Horizon which
really looks like this but it's always
convenient and we all do this all the
time we draw a surface one plank l L
away from that Horizon this is a Surface
one plun length away from the
Horizon all right it's one plank length
from here one plank length here one
plank length here it's a surface if you
like if we wanted to draw this a
different way we would say here's the
Horizon and one plunk length away a thin
layer uh and and the point here of
course is that the Horizon is not really
accurately defined to within a plunk
length Quantum fluctuations not not only
of ordinary particles but of gravitation
and the structure of the Horizon they
all take place so you really should
think of the Horizon is a sort of
slightly thickened thing if you think of
a thickened like that and a fluctuation
takes place then this fluctuation
doesn't occur at time minus infinity it
occurs at some time in the remote past
or in sometime in the past it's emitted
out and it falls back into the horizonal
over
here so somebody outside would say look
I see some photons that look as though
they were emitted from somewhere very
close to the Horizon with very very high
energy they pop out and they fall back
in that's the that's what the
mathematics
gives and
um it uh is the same no matter what the
Horizon is whether the Horizon is a
cosmic Horizon whether it's a uh now for
cos are we oh I guess we ready to begin
yeah after 10 after oh we spent more
time on that than I thought we would all
right well
then um good let's talk about Cosmic
Horizons in the same vein there are many
ways to draw the sitter space the sitter
space is the space which is
exponentially expanded
Landing one way to draw it is just to
draw a Time axis which goes up to
Infinity draw the Blackboard and keep
track of the fact in our heads that the
distance between any pair of
neighboring coordinate lines here is
exponentially increasing with time
that's one way to draw
it another way to draw
it is is
to squash all of future
time all of future
time down by a coordinate transformation
we did the coordinate transformation
last
time so that future
Infinity is a horizontal line like that
corresponds to T equals
infinity I think I wrote down the metric
for you
in a form which Maps tals Infinity to a
finite place I'll just rewrite it for
you uh the original metric was D s^2 is
equal to minus DT ^2 that's the usual
thing
plus e to the 2
HT
dx2 where again dx2 stands for dx2 + D
y^2 + dz^2 and this e the 2 HT that's
the exponential expansion of the space
why does it come in with a
two because it's really distance squared
right distance between points is
increasing like e to the
HT and so a given
DX corresponds to a growing distance
which grows as e to the 2 as e to the HT
and in the metric it's e to 2 HT then we
made a transformation just in order it's
a we made a transformation of the time
variable we wrote the time variable
T I think oh what is
h right H is the Hubble constant in this
space all right it's also the expansion
rate we wrote T is equal I believe to
1/h e minus E to the uh
minus minus or plus um minus minus h t
sorry T capital
T capital T goes from minus infinity
this right minus HT should be
right yeah capital T goes from minus
infinity deep in the
past what happens to this thing when T
goes to minus infinity
it gets big e to the minus HT gets big
when T goes to minus infinity but it
gets big in
negative okay so the remote past tal
minus infinity is also Capital tal minus
infinity but the remote
future when this T gets very
big that happens when
what do I have this right I don't have
this right
excuse me still still true when this T
is large and negative this T is also
large and negative all right but now
what happens when this T is large and
positive when this T is large and
positive then this gets
small and capital T goes to zero so tal
Infinity is also Capital Tal zero and
this is just a trick it's a trick for
getting the whole
geometry or not the whole geometry but
the part we're interested in the remote
future in this case onto the
Blackboard now what happens if we
rewrite this metric in terms of t let me
just remind you it becomes
minus sorry plus minus DT
S Plus the
X2 all time
Time 1 / T ^2 1/ t^2 h^2 to be
exact
notice that when T gets very small the
distance between points gets very big
just as it did on this side over here
this is just a rewriting of this and T
goes to zero is the remote future the
nice thing about writing the metric this
way
is that in these coordinates light rays
move on 45° angles that's very helpful
in thinking about this geometry and
asking who can communicate with
whom let's get rid of this
here why is it the light rays move on 45
degrees in this metric
here well the rule for light rays is
that the metric should be zero that the
interval should be zero
so DT ^2 minus DT ^2 + dx2 = 0 that's
the same as DT = DX right and DTS DX is
just a 45° uh 45 degree line if the
light R was moving in the plane it would
be 45° in the plane if we're moving out
of the plane it would be 45 degre out of
the plane but I you know there's only so
much we can visualize with a two-
dimensional Blackboard okay so that's
the setup that's what the that's what
SpaceTime in this kind of
inflating um exponentially increasing
world looks like here it is now let's
imagine here's somebody you me I don't
know and
um in the real world of course people
only get to live for a certain amount of
time but right now we're going to
pretend we can live forever and so
here's the world line of some
Observer and that World line does it
really end no it doesn't really end
because there's an infinite amount of
time between any finite point in here
but on the Blackboard we draw
The Observer as just ending at that
point over here that's the remote future
what can that Observer
see well he looks back and he sees light
rays coming at him from distant
places and light rays
move on 45 degrees I could uh I can add
one more Dimension to this if I
uh I can fake a dimension by doing
that all right so we see these light
rays coming but I can't get I can't draw
another dimension that's too
many uh we would like X Y and Z but at
least I can get X and Y on the plane on
the diagram here so this observer looks
back and as time goes on gets to see
more and more but never gets to see more
of the SpaceTime than is in the backward
light cone
here so in
particular never gets to see anything
out here or out here at least doesn't
get to see it in any sort of usual
sense so there's a region most of space
and time almost everything is totally
inaccessible to this
Observer now of course there may be
another Observer over here
and that other Observer sees something
else there's some
overlap okay there some overlap but this
person gets to see everything in here
this person gets to see everything over
here let's uh let's uh simplify it and
just study one Observer at a
time for all practical purposes is
Universe SpaceTime universe is this
backward light cone here now what does
he see does he see does he see
things a world which seems to depend on
time you would think so you might think
well everything seems to be
exponentially expanding but let's just
do a very simple exercise
now let's consider this
distance and compare it with this
distance and this distance and this
distance and this distance basically
this this distance that I've drawn here
is the distance from The Observer to his
Horizon let's see how that changes with
time it looks like it's shrinking but
let's just check that here's the
metric here's the metric and let's put
this point over here at T =
-1 let's put this point over here at T =
minus a half this one over here at T =
minus
A4 incidentally that corresponds to
uniform ticking off of proper
time each unit of proper time would
correspond to dividing this interval by
half that's the way this transformation
worked that's why there's an infinite
amount of time in here and now let's
calculate this distance to calculate
this distance we just look at the metric
this is the metric
and
so these two points are separated by a
spatial distance but no time
distance so these two points are
separated by zero time
interval that means in this formula here
there should be an equal sign some words
there should be an equal
sign oh
yeah there is no time separation at all
between these two points so let's write
it in a finite form not a differential
form the square of the
distance let's call it from A to
B what is that no time
separation what is the Delta X between
these two
points can you
tell this is a 45° angle this distance
is capital
T this distance is also capital
T in fact let's not even bother writing
this tal minus1 let it just be t let it
just be T this distance
here the horizontal distance is also the
same as the vertical distance so we get
zero from here but from here we get plus
and Delta X is the same as
t squared
but now divided by T ^2
h^2 and what's the answer 1/ h^
2ar in other words the distance from
here to here is just 1 over
H that's the actual real physical
distance that you would measure with um
measuring
devices but notice the answer doesn't
depend on t
the distance between here and here is
exactly the same as the distance between
here and here the Delta X is
smaller but the t is also
smaller so when you write up to here the
Delta X gets shrunk by a factor of two
but T also gets shrunk by a factor of
two so the distance of the Observer from
The Horizon is always the same the
Observer sees a horizon around him a
sort of
sphere and that sphere doesn't change
with
time in fact you might suspect that if
you used
coordinates that were appropriate to The
Observer inside one horizon you might
discover that the metric had no time
dependence after all the distance to the
hor doesn't have any time dependence
it's always the
same and in fact uh many things don't
change with time it just looks like they
do all right you might expect that maybe
there's some way to rewrite this
geometry and I'm going to I'm simply
going to tell you the answer I'm not
going to work it I'm not going to work
it out in detail but using coordinates
like this spatial
coordinates which are appropriate to the
absolute interior of this Horizon
region all right there is another way of
writing the metric but it's only good
for this
region it doesn't capture what's going
on on the outside but captures
everything on the inside I'm going to
show you what it is and you look at it
for a minute and it may look somewhat
familiar familiar but not
familiar these are
coordinates which are sort of built on
the pattern that I described
here in other words they coordinates in
which the coordinate distance between
here and here is the same as the
coordinate distance between here and
here this coordinate distance and the
new coordinates will be the same as this
will be the same as this and I'll show
you what the what the metric looks
like d s^2 equals minus DT ^ 2 that's no
surprise it's uh it's uh actually proper
time actual proper time and then the
rest of it is
plus oh no no no sorry I did it
wrong
mistake I apologize for mistakes but uh
the mistakes happen when I haven't had
my cookies yet
minus understandable yeah right low
blood
sugar um 1
minus
h^2 r
2 dt^
2 plus 1/ 1 - h^ 2 R 2
d r
2+ R
2 D Omega 2^ 2 remember what Omega 2
is right when you're sitting at the
center and you look around
you you see an angular sphere around you
and this is just one way of not writing
out the full spherical
metric uh just uh simplifying it does
this look at all familiar yeah what's it
look
like it does let me just remind you what
SCH looks like exactly the same except H
there or H squared is replaced by twice
mg and then it's divided by
R everything is exactly the same if you
take the parentheses and put this in
here likewise over
here has the same kind of
form and in fact it looks awfully
different to have H2 r s here but the
important thing what was important where
is the
Horizon and it's s black no right it's
but the Horizon is where this thing is
equal to
zero that's the place where clocks slow
down it's places where distances are
infinitely
contracted and it's also the place which
separates the inside of the black hole
from the outside of the black hole you
can also write this in the form r - 2mg
over R doesn't matter how you write it
the real importance of this term is the
place where it vanishes where it equals
zero that is where the Horizon is
likewise
here same idea the place where this
thing vanishes which is r Where is that
that's r = 1 /
H where is
it R = 1/
H that's the distance to the
Horizon so this is another way of
writing exactly the same
geometry except something really breaks
down if you try to make R bigger
than one over H something goes berserk
here you really don't get out past
here the whole metric gets a little bit
silly space turn and turns into time
times into turns into space we don't
need to worry about that right
now you let R go from zero to 1/ H and
this geometry covers the
entire cone there everything that's
inside that cone and it is everything
that can be seen by an observer by a
single Observer yeah why is
function well because you weren't here
to begin
with because we're talking about an
exponentially expanding Universe right e
to the where the scale factor is e to
the HT all right so your um series of
lines up there
they're all length
one these yeah no up there next drawing
oh here the horizontal ones
yes they're all length one /
H and therefore they're like the
distance to the Horizon here from Ral 0
to
1/h all right it takes a little bit of
mathematical trickery to rewrite this um
metric a few coordinate changes a few
transformations of coordinates that you
have to
do and when you've done those coordinate
Transformations you'll find that this
patch it's called sometimes the causal
patch or the static
patch and one thing you notice about
this metric the most interesting thing
about or the many interesting things
about it first of all it has a horizon
but second of all none of the
coefficients here depend on time they do
depend on R but they don't depend on
time and in that sense in this form form
the metric is completely time
independent and it's another way of
saying that what an observer sees around
him just doesn't change with
time it's
static it always looks the same distance
to the Horizon is always the same
whatever the Observer does at one time
if he does the same thing at a later
time you'll see the same thing now it is
true that if he takes two
particles Let's ignore any forces
between them let's suppose he takes two
particles and lets them go what will
happen no we're ignoring any attractive
forces space between them expands and so
they go flying off so they say well that
doesn't sound time independent but the
point is if he does the same experiment
at a later time he will see exactly the
same thing take the two particles let
them go and they will slowly accelerate
apart from each other take two particles
at a later time do exactly the same
experiment they will slowly accelerate
away from each other do those two
particles see a red shift the other
particle red Shi is that right for sure
for sure
now once we get to this point here we
can kind of see that a black hole
Horizon and a deit space Horizon are
very very close relatives
um the fact that everything that you can
say about the near Horizon region of the
schwarzel black hole is pretty much the
same for the um uh for
the the cter
space I'm not going to try to prove that
but the similarity of the metrics are
pretty clear and they uh in fact near
the Horizon they're almost identical
very close to the horizon but the whole
Global picture of things is quite
different whereas a black hole is
something that we stand on the outside
of and look at and emits Hawking
radiation the whole picture here is
quite the opposite we are on the
inside the black stuff is on the outside
the stuff we can't
see and yes there is hawking radiation
being emitted from The Horizon for the
same reason reason it's emitted and
absorbed emitted and absorbed sometimes
a photon gets to us but we can also ask
the question what is the energy of a
photon by the time it gets from Near The
Horizon to us and there there is a big
red shift
Factor this metric just like the Schwarz
Shield metric has associated with it a
gravitational potential this metric also
has a gravitational potential
I'll draw it for you as a function of
r as a function of r there's a
gravitational potential let's see if we
can draw
it it's upside down it looks like
this the meaning of that is it takes
work to pull something from The Horizon
to the center equivalently an object
emitted from the center as it makes its
way toward the Center will lose energy
will lose potential energy it has to
climb up out of this potential and will
lose energy another way of talking about
red shift you can work out the red shift
easily enough from the metric I'm not
going to do it now but a photon emitted
near the Horizon will lose energy on the
way out here such that the Hawking
temperature the temperature seen over
here is of order
let's see what is it well it's a order
one over the distance from The
Horizon of order one over the distance
from The Horizon in plun
units how big is our Horizon how big is
the Horizon our
uh our Horizon our Horizon meaning to
say the Horizon that we think we know
about on the basis of the known
expansion properties of the universe
this distance one/ H one/
H is
about 20
* 10 to the 9th light
years 20 billion light
years okay the red shift of a
photon from The Horizon to where we
are is by this factor of one over uh
20 * 10 9th that's a lot so the photons
that we see coming from the Horizon are
of incredibly basically the answer is
that the photons that we see have a
wavelength which is about 10 billion
light
years so those are not very energetic
photons we are not likely to see
them right what kind of experiment would
we do to see them well we would do the
same kind of experiment we did with a
black hole
except we do it from the
inside Alice takes her uh fishing pole
and at the end of her fishing pole
instead of a worm she has a thermometer
and she casts it out they got a very
long line of uh fishing cast it out the
expansion of the universe pulls on the
uh thermometer or it tends to be
accelerated out away from her and she
waits 10 billion years or
so there's also a a uh a uh it's not
just a fishing line it happens to be a
coaxial cable or something that that she
can read off the
temperature and she waits 10 billion
light years and then and then and then
puts a thumb on the on the on the
spinning reel to stop it she doesn't
want it to go through the Horizon so it
stops over
here and she waits until the signal
comes back that's another 10 billion
years and she reads off the temperature
and the temperature she'll read off as
high on the other hand if she just sits
here with a
thermometer the temperature that she
sees is red shifted and it's very very
very low you know far lower than
anything that can be produced in the
laboratory it's not in particular the uh
the microwave background temperature has
nothing to do with that it's the
desitter
temperature well that's the
properties of the world that we live in
as it will be a couple of hundred
billion years from now empty apart from
us sitting at the center everything
else having passed out through the
Horizon some amount of stuff
gravitationally bound together might
include our galaxy and a couple of other
galaxies that happen to be not being
dragged away with the uh with the
ambient expansion and everything else
will be essentially empty except for
this very very very very
feeble uh radiation radiation from The
Horizon it's a sort of grim uh Prospect
as various people have noted the
astronomers at that time will be
confused they won't understand uh why
they're alone in a in a very big
universe in fact they'll have a very
hard time measuring how big the universe
is there won't be anything out there to
look at so it will be uh and the
possibility of measur measuring this
radiation well that's not going to
happen either
yeah yes Michael
I
yeah yeah exactly the same as the black
hole here's the black hole from our
perspective in a classical
analysis we would see things getting
closer and closer and closer and closer
and closer to the
Horizon you could say exactly the same
thing over here let's draw
it here's our Observer somebody falls
through the
Horizon our Observer over here never
gets to see them fall through the
Horizon as time goes on for our Observer
here he looks back and as far as he can
tell as time goes on longer and
longer Bob says Alice is getting
flattened against the Horizon yeah so
it's exactly the same as the black hole
basically red shift and then basically
disappear M fade
away so if somebody else that fall
through the exact same
spot okay classically classically just
without worrying about any quantum
mechanics okay here's what he sees
C's may be the wrong term since the
wavelengths of radiation that they send
out get so long that they'll never see
it but here's the mathematical
description let's see all right here's
the
Horizon and here is who was it
Alice there's Alice and what's the other
one
Jane here you are
Jane Alice Falls towards the horizon
and get
squashed Jane gets
closer and they starting to get
squashed Alice gets
closer Jane also gets closer in other
words a kind of sedimentary structure
forms near the Horizon that just
gradually gets closer and closer and
skinnier and skinnier now that's a
classical description what actually
happens Quantum mechanically is more
complicated and involves
emiss interaction with the emitted
radiation and so forth which spreads
them all out over the place and uh and
ionizes them Cooks them does terrible
things to them but from a classical
perspective you would just lose track of
them as they get squashed closer and
closer in there and you'd lose track of
them because the radiation from them
would get more and more and more red
shifted as they get closer and
closer okay
but isn't it the case that Horizons are
only hot for things that get close but
don't cross over if you pass through you
don't get
cooked
okay Alice has no problem at the Horizon
she sails perfectly happily
through Bob just loses track of her but
if he tries to do an experiment which
sees what happens to her we come back to
this very strange
situation this Heisenberg uh microscope
situation where the only way to do an
experiment is to shine some high
frequency light on
Alice and as Alice gets closer and
closer to the Horizon the wavelength of
that light has to get smaller and
smaller so the answer I'm sure by now
you know is that the attempt to look at
her we cook
her
so
uh right yes
Kevin simplistically the um the all
those effects of the Horizon black hole
were caused by the
gravitational well if you will in the
black hole what's the equivalent here
well there is uh there is a
gravitational all right
good all right let's do a little
exercise
for any kind of uh gravitating material
which we usually call Mass but we could
could use the word energy for any kind
of distribution of energy or mass there
is around it or in its neighborhood or
somewhere there's a gravitational
potential all right the gravitational
potential is usually called
fi f is such that its derivative its
gradient is the gravitational force on
an object on a unit Mass on a test Mass
on a unit mass now five satisfies an
equation on the left hand side of the
equation is something involving fi and
on the right hand side of equation is
the mass
density this is Newtonian physics let's
do Newtonian physics what's on the right
hand side let's just say the mass
density which I'll call row and it's a
function of position and general it
might just be a point source at the
center what's the left hand side I've
just written five but of of course
that's not quite right what's the
anybody know the right
the not the Divergence but close you're
close something called Dell
squared which is basically the second
derivative with respect to the distance
R uh DC by Dr R
2 of Five for a radially symmetric
distribution of mass is equal to row
this would give us for example for a
point Mass it would give us the usual
Kum the usual um Newtonian uh potential
energy now vacuum energy is an
interesting possible candidate to put on
the right hand side and let's do so the
is my sign right is Del squ F minus row
or plus
row I can't remember and I'm not going
to try to figure it out it's one or the
other
um this not important all right what
would happen if there were vacuum energy
in addition to the pockets of ordinary
energy that sit there well you would put
a constant on the right hand side what
would the constant be the constant would
be the constant vacuum energy sometimes
called cosmological constant other times
it's just called h squ
it's basically proportional to h
s in fact that's where H comes from so
here's a formula for the gravitational
potential
of a space which is filled with a
uniform distribution of
mass it's the vacuum energy absolutely
uniform not only doesn't it change with
position it doesn't even change with
time uh what's the solution of this
equation
nope easier than
that it's
f equals plus or minus we'll figure out
the sign later h^2 R
2 let's
differentiate well maybe there's a
factor of
two what's the first derivative of
this with respect to
r h squ R what's the second
derivative H
squ that's
this okay so look at that a uniform
absolutely uniform distribution of
energy and there should be a minus sign
here
uh yeah there should be a minus sign
here if we do it
right okay so what we see we see that
there's a potential a gravitational
potential you can think of it as being
due to this uniform distribution of
energy distributed all over space and
what does it look like it looks like
this minus h^2 r^ 2 /
2 right what does this mean this
means okay let's let's follow it a
little bit that's the potential energy
that I I at the center of my
geometry I'm special I'm at the center
of my geometry you may think you're
special in you're at the center of your
geometry and that's fine with me but I
know that I'm special and I'm at the
center of my geometry I make
measurements I make measurements on test
masses and I find they move in various
ways and I find they move as
if they were in a potential which went
like this incidentally what does the
force do to this
potential no
the force is the derivative of the
potential all right so the derivative of
the potential is is just
R so this is a force which increases
it's repulsive that's the minus pushes
you down and the force increases
linearly with
distance so any two objects if you just
start them out at rest they will start
to accelerate away from each other
and they'll eventually start picking up
some speed how long does it take them to
pick up any appreciable speed that
depends on H basically 10 billion years
for it to pick up any significant speed
but if you wait 10 billion years it will
be moving like a
rocket okay so no not like a rocket like
a photon or close to a photon all right
so what is what is all this
mean supposing you start an object right
up at the top literally at the top what
happens to
it stay still it stays there right it's
at a point of unstable equilibrium well
that's another way of saying that me in
my own frame of reference if I take an
object which is located right where I am
it'll stay there you don't have to be
too uh too sophisticated about it if I
am my own object and I don't move away
from myself well not the
you know sometimes but not not usually
okay now what happens if I take an
object a little bit away from
me and again we are ignoring all other
forces we can take into account the
other forces we're ignoring so I start
somebody out at rest 100 meters away
from me that's over here what happens to
them they start moving away and in fact
in this kind of potential they will move
with an accelerated motion that uh that
will be if we take into account
relativity and everything it'll be this
exponential expansion so that's just the
statement that the space in between
things is expanding
exponentially so this kind of picture is
a kind of
Newtonian description of the same
physics as the exponential expansion of
the universe it is as though there was
number one a uniform distribution of
matter around me and number two a
gravitation potential energy which is
pushing everything
away yeah but we do have to consider the
other we certainly
do right so if I took the let's take the
potential energy between you and me only
gravity for Simplicity right there's
another
contribution I'm standing at the center
and I'm thinking about you and I see
that you have an ordinary gravitational
Newtonian potential energy relative to
me in addition to this all right first
of all what would the ordinary
gravitational potential energy look
like it would look like that pulling me
toward the pulling you toward my
Center would look like that one of our
one of our potential all right if I add
that to this
it look something like
that so if I'm close enough if I'm close
enough then I get pulled you get pulled
toward me if I'm right at this distance
or you're right at this distance then
you're in a kind of unstable equilibrium
but if you're slightly farther away than
uh than the top of this then you get
pushed away so this is exactly the
situation that uh the Andromeda galaxy
appears to be in here somewhere where is
falling toward
us a few galaxies away they're
accelerating out away from
us yeah so um so this is a model just B
in the expansion space and it acts as if
it has this gravitational effect then we
did talk in in describing it we also
talk about the vacuum energy which is
it's a Quantum effect has nothing to do
with the and and and it behaves the same
and so they both actually are there
which which are both no no no no no no
no there's one thing you can call it
vacuum energy you can call it
cosmological constant there's only one
thing and if you want to mimic it or
model it in Newtonian physics you model
it by a uniform Mass
distribution right but it's one thing
it's not two vacuum energy cosmological
constant uh dark energy energy all the
same
thing and they all correspond if you as
I said if you want to model it in a
Newtonian context you simply imagine a
uniform uh uh right but on the other
hand we're saying this is also a
consequent consequence of the uh of the
simple expansion of space of the
relativistic well I you can either say
it's a consequence of it or a uh or
cause of it I mean they go together
right
a little bit of expansion say it
again I I say it again pardon me um I do
it it seems that that the same
phenomenon has a completely classical
description and a completely Quantum
description
well the origin of the Dark Energy the
cosmological constant of vacuum energy
is most likely quantum mechanical in
origin
but once it's there it's Just Energy in
fact I mean you know
um the mass of the electron has a
contribution to it which is quantum
mechanical uh but once we know what the
mass is we simply use it in classical
physics as if it were just an ordinary
Mass so while it's quite true that the
dark energy cosmological constant May
ultimately be due to Quantum
fluctuations never nevertheless by the
time we average over those Quantum
fluctuations what we see is a uniform
distribution of energy very small to be
sure if it wasn't
small then we'd be rocketing away from
each
other it's very very
small um in natural units in plunk units
it's something like 10 the minus
123 it's a very very small number
compared to any other natural scale in
physics uh and it sets the scale for and
it's the reason its smallness is the
reason that our Horizon is so big what
would the world be like if that
cosmological constant was much larger in
other words if H was much
larger here's this the distance to the
Horizon sorry one over H what if H was
much much bigger then we'd be surrounded
by a smaller sphere
we would be living in what effectively
looked like a much smaller Universe even
though it was even though what do I say
h being big right if H is
Big that of course means a more rapid
expansion but it also means a smaller
Horizon so we'd be sitting in the
smaller Horizon but with a much larger
repulsion between
things if H were larger the repulsion
would be larger and and the size of the
Horizon would be much smaller so we'd be
much more tightly restricted but we'd
also be subject to a force which would
be you know causing everything to
explode so there is a limit to how big
the Hubble con the um uh the
cosmological constant of the dark energy
can be and we still be able to measure
it we we be able to talk about it it uh
yeah would that mean that there's a
relationship between PL constant which
is related to F of fluctuations and the
cosmological constant yes in a sense
there's a
relationship the language the language
to use is not plunks constant plunks
constant is a thing which carries
Dimensions it's always good to talk
about dimensionless things if you work
in plunk units you're automatically
talking about dimension
things um and of course knowing what the
plunk unit is does involve in in
ordinary um measurement units does
involve knowing what har bar is but
[Music]
um yeah
there're the answer is in plunk units
and that means everything is
dimensionless it means that the Newton
constant is one it means the plunk
constant is one means the speed of light
is one in those units where all the
fundamental constants of physics the
most fundamental constants of physics
are set equal to one in those units the
cosmological constant energy the dark
energy is 123 orders of magnitude
smaller so that's one of the great
puzzles of physics what's the origin of
that very very small number yeah along
those lines I have heard that not all
were and share the the idea that vacuum
energy should be identified with
cosmological cost because of that 12 if
you go out in the world and you start
asking people is the earth flat or is it
round you'll find 40% of Americans don't
know that it's uh
uh and I wouldn't say the situation is
is
um well let's let's be a little bit
charitable it's not quite as
bad yeah no there are some serious
physicists who question it and uh but
and and 10 years ago you might have
reasonably questioned it 10 or 15 years
ago you might have reasonably questioned
it
um the bounds from experiment get
Tighter and Tighter and Tighter what
they mean by saying that the
cosmological constant isn't a constant
is the hypothesis that uh basically that
age varies with time and decreases uh
decreases
decreases and will eventually settle
down to uh uh to
zero the idea that the vacuum energy
whatever it is is a temporary transient
thing which will settle down all right
um and eventually not be there just one
quick question when when they keep
saying on these TV shows about how
everything's get lonely and dark and
we'll be all by ourselves and all that
that we wouldn't even notice the
difference here because you can't see
galaxy6 other than maybe a drama with
the uned eye no a with a telescope you
can yeah but I'm saying without a
telescope we won't even be able to know
oh that's probably
true yeah without a telescope uh
yeah
yep yeah who cares the other thing was
if you say it's perfectly flat you took
perfectly flat and extended it forever
and you tried to pull water and never
fall off the
edge
so you know it's a very interesting
question I've thought about it myself
and I've known other people who thought
about it how would astronomers of that
distant time in the future the Earth is
still here they're still here you know
there's some questions and problems but
nevertheless we're all still here and we
have our Scopes and we've lost our
history books the internet has failed
we've lost our history books and we
don't know very
much uh how might we become aware of the
fact that there was a finite Horizon out
there that there was a dark energy that
things were accelerating away from each
other and it's very very hard to imagine
any I can't think of any way that they'd
be able to
tell uh the the cosmic microwave
background what would happen to
it red shift away it red shifts to the
point where it's completely
undetectable what about the galaxies
that we count in order to measure the
Hubble constant and so forth they're not
there
anymore and it just becomes uh very very
difficult to imagine how they Could
reconstruct
uh new galaxies being born within the
new galaxies are not born from empty
space
no but they they would adding to it with
the dark energy no the dark energy
doesn't won't create galaxies um they
they
would actually before we knew any of
this astronomy there was something
called olders Paradox right and so they
would have to have some explanation for
that no there wouldn't there wouldn't be
any stars out there no there would there
would be our galaxy and as no no our G
Al's Paradox let me remind you Al's
Paradox was about the idea of an
infinite uniform density of stars out to
Infinity if you just take the stars from
within our galaxy how much light do they
give we know how much light they give
ober's Paradox was a paradox of what
happens if the universe is filled with
stars out to infinity and they're not he
didn't know about uh about expansion of
the universe they're just sitting there
no but they wouldn't know about galaxies
so they would just look out and see
stars yeah but they right but they would
see an end to the Stars they would see
the G
have they would see the island universe
that the that astronomers before Hubble
believed includ Einstein including and
but he stuck the uh that cosmological
term in there just in case you know to
make it St so they may make that same
mistake so to speak uh no they would
just they would yeah right the stars in
our galaxy would be smearing against the
Horizon right so they would go out in no
no no no
they'll just be just where they are now
they'll be where are how far how big is
the galaxy 100,000 light years right
small tiny microscopic uh size no I'm
saying that the Horizon will be
shrinking until Horizon doesn't
shrink Horizon doesn't shrink it's
constant no no it's not constant
yet uh it'll be another 20 30 billion
years okay right but we're talking about
100 yes yes and how big will it be in 20
or 30 billion years few Galactic radi no
no no no no no no no it will not be a
few Galactic radi it will be about 20
billion light
years from the dark energy that we know
is there from the measurements of
everything we know about the
cosmological constant is a certain
number how big big enough to put the
Horizon about 20 billion light years
away now
tomorrow basically forever
so they'll be sitting in this big
container uh 20 billion light
years
across with 100,000 Lightyear uh Galaxy
uh that they can see everything else
having been swept
clean and how do they detect the fact
that there is a outer uh boundary let's
call it uh
isn't there some rate at which stars are
ejected from the Galaxy they you know
when they're getting yeah galaxy stars
are stars stars are rejected from Galaxy
that's true you'll have some small
number of objects you can track for a
while you can track them for a while but
you won't be able to track them out the
cosmal you
know well how do we know that that
hasn't
already which stars evaporate from the
Galaxy that you know that edge of the
univers 20 billion L years away yes is
you know we're not able to see the rest
of it we can see it we can see it uh we
can we can
see we can measure the um the expansion
rate and
reconstruct reconstruct
it where there's enough stuff around to
be able to reconstruct it at the present
time suppose the uh the event Ariz will
be just
outside the distance to the adrama the
Galaxy wouldn't the the the that would
be quite noticeable yeah then then You'
be able because the adic Galaxy wouldn't
behave the way it behaves now because
the component with the expansion is so
large yes but it's not the The Horizon
is not going to shrink in the Horizon is
going to be at the place
where yeah it's going to be at with the
numbers that we have today with the
numbers that we have
today well measured checked many
different ways the prediction for the
future is that the Horizon will be at
about 20 billion light
years that's where the that's that's
where it will be yeah in other words H
is constant during uh during this kind
of expansion and um the distance to
where you have to go to where the speed
where you see the speed of light that's
going to be constant yeah uh don't there
be Big Bangs happening out there not
that I know
of I
thought the um what's call the Erse all
the there are yeah but we can't see that
part that's out Beyond the
Horizon that's out Beyond the Horizon
that will not be visible to us or to our
future
descendants now what is true there is
something which is
true uh they're called panker
recurrences I'll tell you what a panker
recurrence is first of all your picture
of that's the inside your picture should
be that there's some temperature here a
very low temperature from our point of
view a very high temperature out near
the boundary but you should think of it
as a thermal system it in fact has an
entropy the entropy is just the area of
the Horizon in plun units it has an
entropy a certain finite entropy and so
you can think of it to a large extent
there's a cavity with a finite amount of
entropy in it and some thermal gas the
thermal gas is mainly out near the
Horizon because of this effect it all
tends to congregate out
here and it's constantly
fluctuating now a thermal system let's
talk about the thermal systems a box
a box of gas with lots of molecules in
it after it comes to thermal equilibrium
and in
fact what will happen is everything will
come to thermal
equilibrium when everything passes out
through the Horizon it will be in
thermal
equilibrium what is a gas a box of gas
like when it's in thermal
equilibrium well it's like nothing I
mean it's a big dull box of uniform
density nothing much happens it just
sits there and uh sits there forever and
ever right black body right yeah if if
it's radiation in there it's a black
body if it's molecules in there the
molecules and they're fairly let's say
they're fairly
dense then apart from tiny little
fluctuations nothing ever happens well
that depends on time scales there are
time scales
basically
statistically anything can happen there
are no rules there are no rules there's
only statistics only probabilities
that's all there are probabilities you
can really ask what is the probability
that all the molecules suddenly come
together in such a way that they all
wind up in the corner of the
room there's an answer to that there's
an answer to that the probability it is
basically e
to the minus the entropy of the gas the
entropy is roughly the number of
molecules of the gas so if we have a box
with 10 the 25th molecules this is e to
Theus 10
25th you wait a time of order e to the
10 the 25th it's called the poner
recurrence
time and basically the poner recurrence
time is the time scale for extremely
rare and unusual fluctuations to take
place
an extremely rare and unusual
fluctuation might be all the molecules
Go off into the center or it might be
they all assemble themselves into an
elephant or
whatever uh that time
scale is of
order what's called a pronay recurrence
time and it's normally extremely huge on
that time scale there's constantly
things going on fluctuations taking
place which take you far far out of
thermal
equilibrium so far out of thermal
equilibrium that in the return to
thermal equilibrium all sorts of
complicated vortices and other things
might form in
this uh before it returns to thermal
equilibrium this is also thought to be
true for the sit space that if you
really wait long enough how
long e to the 10 to the
120 what unit
it doesn't matter what
units believe me it doesn't matter what
units in any units you can think of it
will take e to the 10 to the 120 of
those units and let's say years for
recurrence to occur and on that time
scale all kinds of things will take
place so
uh among other things right right but uh
you know short of such impossibly long
time scales nothing will happen it'll
just be heat death the same kind of heat
death that takes place in here when
everything comes to equilibrium and
there's no more uh interesting things
happening well more mild fluctuations
Could Happen fluctuations could happen
I'll give you an example of a
fluctuation that can happen we can even
give a rough estimate of how long
between such
fluctuations instead of the whole world
returning to the original Big
Bang which might happen that would be
this time scale here we could ask for a
more modest kind of fluctuation a more
modest kind of fluctuation might be a
fluctuation happens in which a solar
system accidentally forms I told you an
elephant could form okay yes an elephant
can form and the time scale for
elephants to form is not e to the minus
the entropy of the whole gas gas it's e
to the minus the entropy of an elephant
what's the entropy of an elephant
roughly the number of molecules in
it uh in the same way if you wait long
enough by accident by pure thermal
fluctuation a solar system might form
here that might be the cheapest way of
making an
observer right the cheapest way
probabilistically speaking of making an
observer might be for a fluctuation to
happen and to create a solar system but
I can think of something a little
cheaper I can think of just the Earth
forming right that would be even cheaper
the entropy of the earth is well you
might worry a little bit if there was no
sun then uh then you wouldn't have any
warmth but let's not worry about that
you might form an already warm Earth
that keeps itself warm for some period
of time and you say well maybe it's not
enough time for people to uh to um to uh
evolve don't worry about it the
fluctuation involves the creation of
people too okay but you could even do
cheaper if all you want as a single
Observer you could imagine a single
Observer or just his
brain just his brain being nucleated by
random fluctuation such things are
called boltzman
brains and serious physicists worry
about Computing the relative probability
of ordinary observers with with a
reasonable history like us versus
boltzman brains they don't want a
universe in which um in which the
typical Observer is a boltzman
brain that's not a good thing if when
you calculate the properties of the
universe that you find out that the
overwhelming majority of observers are
boltzman brains that appear
spontaneously out of nowhere and uh and
serious physicists worry about uh about
whether their cosmology will be
dominated by boltzman brains instead
of uh darwinian brains that
evolved I'm not kidding you this is and
and it's a serious
business that Ancient Aliens maybe a
quicker way would just be to set someone
out even though quicker way to do what
to determine whether uh in the future
when you your history books internet
crash to determine whether or not the
you just because it might be billions of
years but then you might be able to see
that no no you're right I I I should
qualify my statement that it's
impossible to it's impossible to do it
except on time scales which are big
enough to explore such large
regions right that's exactly right um
these forces are such that they only
become appreciable at distance scales of
let's say some fraction of a billion
light
years so yes if you could go out and
explore yes of course you're right that
that's a much shorter time scale you
could go out and send out your explorers
map out the geometry of uh with light
signals um measure the properties of
space on large scale space and time and
if you had yourself a few billion years
to do it in and Rockets that could get
out there and explode that large size
yes then you could definitely
tell uh but if you're restricted
to you know the usual lifetime of uh of
an experiment well just any kind of
ordinary time scales you would have a
much harder time telling and I'm not
sure how you would do
it uh yeah but absolutely right you
could imagine sending out explorers to
map out geometry and they would find uh
they would find this yeah so the time
scale of the experiments would be red
shifted well no the time scale of the
experiments would be of order uh few
billion light year a few billi I'm just
saying that it takes longer the more you
wait it takes longer the more you wait
longer to do the experiments to find out
what we know now yes it would take much
longer to do the experim yes that's
right that's right the Observer sending
oh no no I think you're right it is it
is a matter of red shift in a sense yes
The Observer sending information back
sends a radiation that is modula M
that's red shift that's okay um we don't
even do that don't even think about it
just send the observers out let them
make measurements with light rays the
light rays take a billion years to get
from one place to another that's okay we
have a billion years and then just bring
the observers back and uh and and you're
right there is a red shift Factor but we
Face exactly the same red shift Factor
when we measure it today we measure
today the cosmological constant by
monitoring the um uh the cosmic macave
background that's been red shifted by a
factor of a thousand or so or
so so so what is the what is the
information content of a highly red
shifted signal you don't have to Red
shift that much if you want to
explore the Universe on a scale of let's
say 4
billion light years on a sun
and that's that's enough that is
probably a billion light years would be
more than enough to detect uh the
expansion the in a billion light years
the red shift is a small is a is not a
big deal it's a small fraction of one a
tenth or something like that so you're
not limited by Red shift in making these
measurements if you were we wouldn't be
able to do them today
the planets and so not the planets the
stars and galaxies that we see out there
that we count and which form our
measuring rods and so forth those are
out pretty far a few billion light
years um but we're not limited by in
detecting them by their red shift from
us since we're talking about funay
recurrence probabilities and of course
all this stuff is based on you know
Quant mechanics Quant field the No No
that does um
yeah P recurrences are not quantum
mechanics they're classical I'm not I'm
not that's true
but but all this is based on predictions
on the kind of laws of nature that we
are aware of today what's the
probability that in the future humans
will discover laws about nature that'll
make all this wrong probably
one just but you know I yes no your
point is well taken but it's also true
that um the most Ro single
robust set of rules that has never been
shaken at all are the rules of
thermodynamics and statistics so if I
had to bet uh on which laws would be
most likely to survive for a very long
time arbitrarily long time I would guess
those which were based on statistics
probability Theory namely statistical
mechanics but do we know no I would also
make the point that
statistics and probability what they
ultimately mean is also something that
is quite misc curious and we might have
a different view of it yes I I think we
will have a different view of it I was
going to talk about uh let's see what
what time is it it's an hour it's an
hour
what I know I know I know what time is
it
really all
right I I yeah I thought I would amuse
you with some other uh things that that
that physicists worry about today that
sound very bizarre I'm just going to ask
if this is a good time to bring in that
question that you brought up about the
ultraviolet red connection I mean
uh infrared infrared
connection yeah I I never quite get to
it do I no
yeah yeah it is the right time but I'm
not going to do it
anyway may I come back for another 10
years yeah someday we'll get to it
someday we'll get to it I was going to
tell you about um a puzzle that has to
do with probability theory that is
really sort of obsessing a lot of
physicists and I'll tell you where it
comes
from the first thing which we're not
going to talk about tonight is the idea
of except I'm just going to mention it
it's the idea of Eternal inflation I'll
draw a picture of it for for what it's
worth and then I'll tell you what the
nature of the puzzle is first we want to
get a picture on the Blackboard a
picture of the sitter space or a
expanding uh inflating Universe looked
like that everything below here is the
world everything above there doesn't
mean anything and this is the end of
time okay one of the things that was
discovered though sometime in the 1970s
by physic by the name of Sydney Coleman
was that the de space like this is
probably
unstable and but it's unstable in a very
specific way it's
unstable with respect to nucleating
little bubbles in which the cosmological
constant might be
smaller all right I'm just going to draw
you what the picture looks like if a
bubble nucleated over here in which the
cosmological was a little bit smaller
maybe a lot smaller what would
happen is a region would
grow we grow and
eventually fill up a region of space
like
that this region of space in here this
region of SpaceTime in here is itself an
entire
universe don't ask me why it's a bubble
but it's an expanding bubble and that
expanding bubble expands out to
something infinitely big up here and it
corresponds in some sense to a
universe with time many of these bubbles
will
form and in fact the population of them
will exponentially increase why it has
to do with the exponential expansion the
population will exponentially
increase and this is a picture that
cosmologists love to draw
these different bubbles could be
different from each other it's not
really terribly important they might be
different from each other things go on
in
them and this process is imagined to
keep going and going and going now each
one of these tiny little bubbles is as
big as the original one I drew here for
the same
reason that this line here is as big as
that line
it's just that they occur
later and they fill up all of future
Infinity here with a kind of fractal
structure of exponentially increasing
population there could be people in
there there could be whatever you like
the populations exponentially increase
there are some very funny puzzles about
probability Theory having to do with um
exponentially increasing populations and
they have really gotten in our way I'll
give you some examples just for fun I'll
tell you some examples and then I'll
tell you how it uh how it applies to
this imagine the
following gunan World thought uh it's
not an experiment it's just a world in
fact it's not a g Duncan world it is our
world it's a world in which the
population is exponentially increasing
unfortunately this is approximately
true okay
number two it's a world with finite
resources I think it's true yeah but
let's take it to be the case that for
one reason or another that nobody really
has the vaguest idea what the total
resources
are this I think is not true unless
unless unless you're in
Congress one half of Congress
anyway right yeah so we will take it
these citizens who live in this uh in
this exponentially growing uh population
they really don't know they have no idea
at all what the resources
are but they are interested in the the
probability that uh they want to know
what the probabilities are that their
resources will last for another
generation or so how can they give how
can they give an answer to this if they
don't know what the resources are but
we'll add one one more postulate and the
one more postulate is one that we always
make in science I'll give you some
examples of it and it is that we who are
doing the experiment are
typical typical means the following it
means that if there are a great many
possible
outcomes but uh more but by some large
majority The Observers who are doing
this have a a large probab well let's
see how to say this yeah okay let's talk
about let's talk about coin flippers
let's talk about coin flippers I hate to
digress but let's uh let's get into coin
flippers we got zillions and zillions of
these people who are obsessed with coin
flipping and what they love to do is
they love to flip a coin a million
times all of these people do this and
they count how many heads they get and
they count how many tails what they do
with it I don't know all right but a
typical one of them or one of them asked
the question what bet should I make for
how many heads and tails do I get not
exactly but you know within some
reasonable bounds I'm going to do an
experiment I'm an experimental physicist
all experiments involve statistics
especially in quantum mechanics and when
we make predictions we're making
predictions analogous to the prediction
of coin
flippers uh who uh flip coins well
what's the answer the answer is there
are some coin flippers who flip all
heads there are some coin flippers who
flip all
Tales according to the standard theory
of probability the overwhelming majority
flip about what did I say a million
million flips a million plus or minus a
thousand square root of of n right so if
you're at all smart and you're a good
experimental physicist and you know the
rules of Statistics you will put down
your prediction your prediction will be
what did I say half a million plus or
minus a thousand half I think I probably
said it wrong half a million plus or
minus a thousand that'll be your best uh
that'll be your best guess and if you're
very far away from it you'll probably
say there was something you probably
won't believe that you are an outlier
you're more likely to believe that your
theory was just wrong but there are
going to be those people who are
outliers and they of course will believe
their theory is wrong and they'll be
wrong we always make the assumption that
we are typical so in this expanding
population let's make the assumption
that we are typical we are like the
majority of all observers who ever lived
then what bet do we make for how long
the uh the resources will last after our
after the present time now the last one
well not necessarily the last one but
there won't be more than two or three
generations after us and the reason is
in an exponentially expanding population
like now about half the people who ever
existed exist now about 3/4 of the
people who ever existed existed within
two generations about 7/8 within three
generations so if we're typical in an
exponentially expanding population we
are near the end of that expansion we're
near the end of that expansion now
that's a very puzzling conclusion it
doesn't it it sounds like there's
something wrong with it how can you
possibly know that if you don't know
what the uh what the resources are on
the other hand it is true that no matter
what the resources are
the most people will be near the end of
the
resources right this is a I give you
I'll give you another example of this
kind of exponential expansion you've all
seen I'm sure you've seen the uh it's my
favorite drawing I I come back to it
over and over again because it has some
deep mathematical significance it's
esher's drawing called limit Circle
Number Four right you all see it's
angels and devils and I'm not going to
try to draw angels and Devils but it has
a big Angel let's just restrict
ourselves to Devils I prefer Devils it
has a big devil in the center it has
smaller Devils out
here it has smaller Devils out
here and so forth now in fact the
geometry is such that they're really all
identical to each
other there are symmetries of this
diagram which move points which can move
this point into this point it'll move
this point into something small over
here
it's just the way that it's drawn makes
some things look smaller and some things
look bigger it's completely symmetric
but of course when eer actually drew it
he did have to draw the small things
small and the big things big
now
um here's the
question let's define an angel with
devil excuse me a devil which has been
drawn with a body part missing let's
call him an amputee okay definition of
an ampute if the devil was drawn with
some body part missing we'll call him an
amputee now these Devils go to sleep and
they wake up in the morning and they
Wonder am I one of the Mis the
unfortunate amputees or am I one of the
uh one of the the whole uh
Devils okay uh if you look at escher's
drawing and you extrapolate as's drawing
past the last visible devil and you
believe that you can extrapolate it you
look you'll see Esha was awfully good at
drawing he didn't draw any Devils with
missing body parts so your conclusion
would be but very high probability
you're not an amputee okay on the other
hand eer had finite
resources finite patience finite time
finite amount of ink right and that
means as he got tired out near the very
very edges surely very very close to the
edges you'll find that almost all of the
angels and Devils will be slightly mdra
right of course they will be they won't
have heads or they won't have tails or
whatever it is the ones out near the
boundary now what is the ratio of the
ones which are adjacent to the boundary
to the all of them do you know the
answer no no there are about as many out
near the boundary as there are in the
whole thing not
obviously there are fewer in the
boundary factor of a
half and that's because the number of
them grows
exponentially as you make bigger and
bigger circles here they grow
exponentially and so if you actually
count if you if you cut it off let's say
by putting a uh circle around here now
count all the ones that are adjacent to
the circle and all the ones on the
inside you'll find they about equal
it's the same mathematics as saying
about half the population no matter how
long into the
past uh the population had been growing
for today about half the
population one generation constitutes
about half the population of anything
that ever existed in the same
way about half of the devils are right
on the edge wherever the edge is we
don't have to know
how much resources eer
had it doesn't matter how much he had no
matter how much he had as he draws more
and more and more of them the ones near
the edge will always be about half of
all of them and so if you wake up in the
morning and you don't know whether
you're a whole devil or half a devil the
chances are about 50% that you're half a
devil that you're an
Ute this is very puzzling because you
could say well
how can I say that when I don't know how
much resources there were well the
answer is it doesn't matter how much
resources there
were okay now we come back to
here we are again facing a problem of
exponential
uh population
growth in this case population of little
bubble
universes oh oh let me come back let me
come back to let me come back to uh to
um angels and Devils for a minute come
back to angels and Devils for a minute
before we go on to
universes eer did have angels and
Devils let's ask a different question
the different question being when you
wake up in the morning are you an angel
or a
devil 50% probability right there are as
many angels as Devils and the
mathematics ofer's drawing if it went on
for Infinity in some sense that would be
true but we know that erer had finite
resources which means we have to draw an
edge to this the answer for the ratio of
devils to uh to Angels is extremely
sensitive to the way we draw that
line it's extremely sensitive to the way
where we could draw the line for example
every time we come to an angel let's go
around it that way every time we come to
a devil we go around it that way and now
we push this Edge out further and
further by a factor of about 3/4s we
will have more Devils than Angels it's
all in the edge here it's all in the
edge and so the assignment of
probabilities to Angel or deviless is
just extremely sensitive to what eer
did just as he was running out of
resources it's ridiculous because uh you
know you you you simply don't know
anything about his resources you would
think that the answer was 50/50 but if
at the end he had a little bit less pink
paint than than white paint the answer
would be many many more white than pink
okay same exact thing here you want to
know the relative probability of
different kinds of bubble universes
forming blue one pink ones and so
forth the population is exponentially
growing how do you decide you try to
decide the same way you say let's chop
this off at some time and count the
number of blue ones versus pink
ones but the problem is the answer is
Super Hyper sensitive to the exact way
that you draw this
line and that has led to a problem that
cosmologists physicists like myself call
The Measure problem measure as in
probability measure how do you assign
probabilities in a world of
exponentially increasing
populations the answer always is it is
extremely sensitive to the way that you
cut things off to the way you uh and
your imagination in the
universe uh this is a very very big
problem for cosmologists because they
want to be able to use their theories in
a pred predictive way and make
predictive um predictive
predictions what the kind of prediction
is there or best or if not predictions
at least explanations of things and so
in this kind of world if it's really
true that there's an exponentially
increasing um population we run into new
kinds of questions about probability
Theory and about how the use of
Statistics which really just um have uh
baffled really baffled us my guess is of
course that we're asking the wrong
questions we're probably asking the
wrong
questions
um but that doesn't help to say that
we're probably asking the wrong
questions it doesn't help unless you can
say what the right questions are and
yeah is there any connection to the
renormalization or to the odd and even
strange which odd and even but I
remember it it's odd and even strange
but the suppos the
uh uh fironic strin where uh the uh
number of D call it sorry the number of
quantum mechanical oscillators varies
the spin of the string well there are
there are relations with renormalization
Theory there are relations with
renormalization Theory renormalization
theory is also a
situation
where again you start your picture of
the world as having a finite number of
degrees of freedom per unit volume and
then you double the number of degrees of
freedom in each volume and then you
double it again and you double it again
you don't double it really you double it
in your imagination and ask how things
converge what we're talking about of
course is you you start picturing the
world as a
lattice you can't handle a continuous
Infinity of degrees of Freedom so you
start the world as a lattice and you
make your
calculations uh based on one degree of
Freedom per unit uh compant wavelength
of an electron or something in Quantum
electrodynamics then you say I want more
accuracy so I divide the world in every
cell and half
again and I recalculate and in each case
I ask the same kind of questions what's
some relative population of uh regions
of space with this property or that
property and again not with respect to
real honest time but with respect to
your mathematical sequence of
descriptions the population is
exponentially increasing again you get
infinite answers you have to deal with
those Infinities and in Quantum field
Theory there are techniques for asking
questions which are not sensitive to the
uh let's call them the edge effects to
the
there are techniques for extracting out
things which are not sensitive to the
details of how you chop this
up so yeah there are there are
correspondences and similarities between
questions in Quantum field Theory and
these kind of questions in cosmology and
people are trying to exploit those
similarities but not I must say with any
great success
here bubble is that like uh uh similar
to inflation going to the current
universe or something like that
yeah yeah well what's called Eternal
inflation
creating yeah it's deeply connected with
the inflationary
Theory can two nucleations be close
enough that they interact
MH and if they did we should see it on
the sky there a little funny uh patch on
the sky there are funny patches on the
sky and there are again very serious
physicists astrophysicists cosmologists
trying to sort out the details of what
you would see on the sky if two of these
bubbles
collided we more or less know you'd see
a small patch on the sky which had a
little either a little colder or warmer
temperature uh and of course you do see
patches on the sky with a little bit of
warmer and colder
temperature uh but uh to be more
detailed you'll have to and you know get
really detailed to see that that's what
they are one of the details would be the
polarization of the microwave background
around them it's kind of interesting if
you saw one of these patches in the sky
and there is one it's called a cold spot
a cold spot and nobody knows what it's
do to it's a cold spot on the sky cold
spot in the sense of microwave
background all right cold spot it's a
candidate for a spot where another
bubble collided with our bubble it's a
candidate
what more can you say about it other
than it's a candidate well you can try
to work out in more detail what such a a
patch would look like and so for example
you discover that uh that light is
polarized in particular this is the
direction of polarization around this in
a particular characteristic way and
people are doing this they're working
out the consequences of such a bubble
Collision Of course
should this be
confirmed this that it is that it does
look like a bubble collision and in
detail it does this of course would be a
major major revolution in uh in
cosmology the discovery and
detection of other bubbles which
collided with our bubble would be very
very
major so the difference is that the
inflation Factor the uh the H in these
these regions that distinguishes the
bottom from yeah the tops is is the
bottom region expanding faster or bottom
region typically is expanding faster and
our region somewhere in here and it had
a history of different expansion
rates you
know yeah so it's it's complicated it's
a complicated story but it does include
this idea of exponential uh uh
population growth so one could foresee a
situ sitation in which we truly
confirmed that there were bubble
collisions with our world we would have
confirmed something like this picture at
least a piece of
it then it becomes a really serious
matter to try to get predictive and to
ask what the relative probabilities of
different kinds of bubbles are and
that's where we run into this trouble of
um exponential
population uh the answers would be very
dependent on the question of whether
they were finite resources or not what
is the finite resources I don't know
what finite resources just this it comes
to an end somehow and the details of the
way that it came to an end would be uh
would uh determine what relative
probabilities
were Collide just add the uh
the dark energies of the two types no
it's more complicated than that the
place where they Collide depending on
details uh there's something called a
domain wall which separates
them and the domain wall on one side has
one Behavior the domain wall on the
other side has another Behavior but the
point is the domain wall would be
visible to us or could be visible to
us it
uh we would need a bit of luck here we
are here's our
Observer if the domain if the um Bubble
collides over
here some of bubble Collision over here
this Observer doesn't get to see
it but if it collides over
here then he does get to see it so
there's different scenarios different
situations but it does it doesn't seem
totally out of the question with the
numbers that we know that there could be
bubble collisions that there could be
visible bubble
collisions and if
so they have a particular signature a
particular Behavior they're fairly
characteristic and um if the dark if the
cold spot is such a bubble Collision we
will know we will know in
time what do I bet well I'm you know I
don't know what to bet honestly do the
bubbles have four dimensions yeah well
it could
yes the curvature of expansion about the
curvature of expansion it's orave or
FL that that some different
things um these bubbles are usually
negatively curved Freedman Roberts and
Walker universes they have negative
spatial curvature the bubble Collision
would certainly modify the the curvature
in some characteristic way but it
wouldn't turn the world from a world
with a negative curvature to positive
curvature that that it couldn't do but
um uh yeah kind of related question but
is it possible to assign a
probability uh to the statement that
string theory is correct or uncorrect
given that we have almost no empirical
evidence one way or another I don't
think
so
5050 that's that's a matter of
individual uh opinion for which which I
don't think there's any value in trying
to assign a possibil probability no but
I mean is there any any and I'm not even
sure I'm not even sure I know what it
means all right I'll give you I'll give
you an answer that I've given
before there is a mathematical structure
a very precise mathematical structure
which exists it's mathematically
consistent uh mathematicians have won
big prizes for uh for uh for proving uh
theorems that were first suggested by
theorists uh on the basis of string
theory which the mathematicians didn't
know so the consistency of the the
internal consistency of it has been
extremely well checked there is a
structure the structure has gravity and
it has quantum mechanics in it so in
that sense string theory is a
welldefined
exact now of course there's a very
remote possibility that somebody will
discover an inconsistency in it but it
seems extremely unlikely and
mathematical
inconsistency um on the other hand that
part of it which is mathematically
precise let's call it String Theory with
a capital S with a capital letters
String Theory
capitalized it is super symmetric
it is
um it's super symmetric the world is not
super
symmetric the world as we see it is not
symmetric the mathematical structure
which is well defined and for which we
have a lot of confidence that it really
exists you can call it quantum gravity
with super
symmetry uh it is not the real world so
in that sense we know now no question
string theory is not the Right
theory
okay 100% we know it for
sure
the
break breaking the Symmetry nobody
really knows how to do okay it is not
part of the mathematically precise part
of the
theory we all expect that this thing
that we call Capital string theory
there it is string theory it has many
many many different
versions a huge number of different
possibilities lie within
this we all expect that it's contained
within something bigger something bigger
that we don't know how to
analyze it's more or less like the
situation where maybe it's like the
situation where physicists in the time
ceeding Newton might have
discovered
the formula fals Ma and the formula the
force is equal to M1 M2 * G / R 2 but
they didn't have the mathematical tools
to analyze anything but the simplest
orbits so they said all right we will
use symmetry the symmetry of circular
orbits we need one little bit of extra
information we need to know the
acceleration of a circular orbit that's
not too hard you can do it on the basis
of some simple symmetries and you can
therefore figure
out um uh Kepler's which one of the laws
is it that
the one of the Kepler laws which tells
you the period is a function of
radius right you know you know that the
theory that you're working with the
theory of circular orbits is not correct
but you just don't have the mathematical
power to be able to go beyond
it I don't know if that's what the real
situation is but it could be like that
so we know that the theory of circular
orbits is contained in something bigger
don't know how to analyze it we know
that the perfectly idealized super
symmetric String Theory the one that we
really know how to analyze is not the
real world it looks a little bit like
the real world but it's not the real
world and the question is whether it's
contained in something bigger which we
could call String Theory with a small
s but the answer is we don't know very
much about this we know a great deal
about
this this has been enough to tell us all
sorts of things about the combination of
gravity and quantum mechanics things
about black holes things about um all
kinds of
things
but to say one way or another what's the
probability that string theory contains
a or that there is an extension of it a
bigger version of it that contains our
world right over
here I don't
know
um of course in some sense well of of
course that's true our world is
someplace here's the theory of someplace
if you add this to this you get
something bigger but uh that's not
helpful we want want to know whether in
some interesting way the theory of the
real world is some
extrapolation from what we already know
and that that that there's no there's no
way to
know does it contradict the string
theory contradict possibility only
Capital string does it contradict the
possibility that what does the capital
String Theory rule out this the the
capital String Theory doesn't rule out
the presence of that doesn't rule out
the existence of small String
Theory but what it does say is that
nature is not as we know it is not
described by Capital String
Theory all right so we know with
certainty that a bigger structure has to
be found and whether that bigger
structure that contains our world will
sort of be contiguous with connected to
the smaller structure of capital String
Theory this we don't know we can all
make our
bets say String Theory does have has no
no symmetries of breaking like the the
particles and things like that people
write loads and loads of papers about
the symmetry breakings of string theory
the S the Symmetry breakings in
particular are the symmetry breakings of
super Symmetry and we know a lot about
the mathematics of super symmetry but we
don't
know a precise version of how to combine
the breaking of super symmetry with
string theory that that is outside the
scope of what we know that doesn't stop
people from
um you know you make an approximation
here and there and then you start
rolling and you can do some things the
problem is that you're making
approximations but you don't know what
those approximations are approximations
to you make some standard approximations
that we use all the time and you start
calculating but there's no backbone to
the thing that you're approximating
so at the present time I think um I
think uh the safest thing to say is
string theory as we know it and as we
can uh the rigorous version of it is
certainly not the real world there's in
my view lots of reason to think that the
part of it that we know about is not the
whole thing that it could be bigger it
probably is almost certainly bigger but
how to say whether the real world is
part of it uh that's very much a
Prejudice that different uh physicists
share in different
proportions does string theory it
contains gravity does it contain special
relativity or a special relativity a
postulate for stram Theory no it
really it really does require special
relativity now special relativity can be
violated by the environment
we're sitting here in a room where
everybody's at rest right and the world
does not look a lorensen variant to me
your presence here violates my sense of
Loren and variance it also violates we
talked about this last time didn't we
yeah uh so you can have what physicists
called a background which means stuff in
it which uh which uh picks out a
particular frame of
reference but the underlying rules the
underlying rules for uh for string
theory do have Lenin variance it's a
prediction it's not a
PO yeah I would say it's a prediction
but the most robust yeah I think so but
the most robust prediction is that it
has
gravity there's just no way for it to
not have gravity it has gravity but is
it consistent with Einstein's theory of
general relativity yeah it is I mean the
background Independence the co the
general coar is in the Str
a yeah this question about background
Independence is a confusing one that
uh uh that
um
uh yeah it is it is background
independent up to a point up to a point
yes
um it's hard to change the ASM totic
boundary conditions continuously but it
should be hard to change the ASM totic
boundary conditions continuously how do
you change ASM totic uh boundary
conditions continuously you can't do any
operation that would change them uh but
short of ASM totic boundary conditions
changing the background locally in
SpaceTime yeah String Theory does have
that uh um and uh you don't have to take
my word for it uh there up there this uh
this is something that's been long
studied since the 1980s
um uh works of people like Curtis Kalen
and other people have have studied
that
um
so no we're gonna we'll finish
tonight
y okay
so for more please visit us at
stanford.edu